Guide to the Pennsylvania Radiological Society Records, 1916-1984 AIS.1992.01
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Pennsylvania Radiological Society Records
1916-1984
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Pennsylvania Radiological Society
AIS.1992.01
11.25 Linear Feet (6 boxes)
This collection consists of the records of the Pennsylvania Radiological Society for the years 1916-1984. The Society is a professional medical organization established in Altoona, Pa., in 1916. In 1969 the Society became a chapter of the American College of Radiology. The collection contains the history, constitution and by-laws, correspondence, minutes, agendas, publications, and membership records of the Society.
History
The Pennsylvania Radiological Society began as the Roentgen Ray Society of Central Pennsylvania organized in Altoona, Pa., in May 1916. The Society's founders were Doctors G. D. Bliss, W. A. Reily, and Harry W. Stewart. The Society was a social meeting place for doctors and students of radiology. The purpose of the Society was to discuss issues related to X-Ray diagnosis, X-Ray/or radium treatment, and medical advancements of the time.
The Society's membership rose steadily into the 1920s with the increase of professionals practicing radiology. Membership spread from central Pennsylvania to include Pittsburgh and Williamsport, Pa., In 1929 at the 14th annual Fall meeting the Society's name was changed to the Pennsylvania Radiological Society. In the 1930s the Society expanded its radiology concentration to include Nuclear Medicine.
In 1969 the Society was recognized as a chapter of the American College of Radiology. The Society's publication The Pennsylvania Journal of Radiology ran from 1933-1950 until its name was changed to The Bulletin of the Pennsylvania Radiological Society in 1951. The PA Radiological Society continues to function today as a chapter of the American College of Radiology.
Scope and Content
This collection contains the records of the Pennsylvania Radiological Society for the years 1916-1984. Most of the records are in the form of correspondence from officials or committees of the Society. Series I contains records pertaining to the administrative function of the society which includes constitution and bylaws and Board of Director's minutes. Series II consists of the correspondence of the Society's founder W. A. Reily, other officials, and professional organizations. Series III consists of committee records that are in the form of correspondence. Series IV contains the membership records of the society. Series V contains the Society's publications and research on various topics which are arranged by subject. Additional notes about the collection are located at the series level.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These records were transferred from the Falk Medical Library, University of Pittsburgh in 1992.
Previous Citation
Pennsylvania Radiological Society Records, AIS.1992.01, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Pennsylvania Radiological Society, ais 92:1, Records, 1916-1984, Archives of Industrial Society, Hillman Library, University of Pittsburgh
Health and medicine; Societies; Radiology -- Pennsylvania; Pennsylvania Radiological Society; Roentgen Ray Society of Central Pennsylvania
- Administration, 1918-1983; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  Series I contains the administrative records of the Society. The records are organized alphabetically and then arranged chronologically. The majority of the records span 1960-1980.
  - Activities and Announcements, 1968-1970 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Annual Meetings, Agendas, 1969-1980 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Annual Meetings, Attendance, 1961-1968 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Annual Meetings, Brochures, 1918-1983 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 19th Annual Meeting, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Annual Meetings, Registration Book, 1933-1954 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Annual Meetings, Society Meetings, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Articles of Incorporation, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Board of Directors, Meeting Agendas, 1960-1968 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Board of Directors, Meeting Agendas, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Board of Directors, Meeting Agendas, 1974-1976 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Board of Directors, Meeting Minutes, 1967-1969 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Code of Ethics, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Constitution and By-Laws, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Constitution and By-Laws, 1955-1980 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Handbook of Chapter Administration, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - History of the PA Radiology Society, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Lancaster County Meeting, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Outline of Radiology by Educational Committee, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Pennsylvania College of Nuclear Medicine, Meeting Minutes, 1976-1978 (Box 1, Folder 20-22)
  - President Elections, Audiograph discs, 1956-1957 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - President Elections, 1956-1957 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - President Elections, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Presidents, 1958-1972 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Radiology Fee Schedules, 1959-1967 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Radiological Conference, Boston, Massachusetts, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Society Agendas (Secretary's Records), 1973-1976 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Statement Before Financial Management Seminar by John Larkin Thompson, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1916-1980; II.
  Series II contains correspondence from many of the Society's officials and corresponding organizations. The records are arranged alphabetically. The series contains the correspondence of W. A. Reilly, the founder of the Pennsylvania Roentgen Ray Society which predated the Pennsylvania Radiological Society.
  - American College of Radiology, 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - American College of Radiology, 1972-1974 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - American College of Radiology, 1976-1980 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Board of Censors, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Councilors to American College of Radiology, 1959-1971 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Etter, Lewis E., 1947-1955 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Etter, Lewis E., 1957-1958 (Box 2, Folder 9-10)
  - Etter, Lewis E., 1958-1962 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Etter Curriculum Vitae, 1961-1965 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Etter Curriculum Vitae, 1966-1970 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Etter Curriculum Vitae, 1967-1968 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Falk Library, 1958-1962 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Greening, Roy R. (Treasurer), 1967-1969 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Hartman's Storage Company, 1962-1969 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Hospital of the University of PA, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Kinsey, Frank R. (Treasurer), 1965-1967 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Kinsey, Frank R. (Treasurer), 1969-1970 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Medical Society of PA, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Miller, Marlyn W. (Editor), 1968-1969 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - PA Society of X-Ray Technicians, 1959-1961 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Philadelphia Roentgen Ray Society, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Pittsburgh Roentgen Ray Society, 1962-1969 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Reilly, W. Edgar (Founder), 1916 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Reilly, W. Edgar (Founder), 1922-1930 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Reilly, W. Edgar (Founder), 1931 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Reilly, W. Edgar (Founder), 1932 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Reilly, W. Edgar (Founder), 1933 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Reilly, W. Edgar (Founder), 1934-1943 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Rominger, Jules, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
  - Rominger, Jules, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Stern, Arnold H. (Printer), 1960-1968 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Tristan, Theodore A., 1968-1970 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Tristan, Theodore A., 1974 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Tristan, Theodore A., 1975 (Box 3, Folder 7-9)
- Committees, 1957-1976; III.
  Series III consists of committee records in the form of correspondence. The records document the committee's function in the Society and beyond. The records are arranged alphabetically.
  - AD HOC Committees, Chiropractor Committee, 1963-1967 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - AD HOC Committees, Committee on Blue Shield Implementation, 1958-1966 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - AD HOC Committees, Committee on Constitution and By-Laws, 1965-1968 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - AD HOC Committees, Insurance Committee, 1967-1969 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - AD HOC Committees, Liason Committee, 1964-1966 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Archives Committee, 1964-1976 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - By-Laws Committee, 1957-1970 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Economics Committee, 1969-1972 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Executive Committee, 1957-1958 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Executive Committee, 1960-1967 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Executive Committee, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Executive Committee, Meeting Agendas, 1968-1970 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Exhibits Committee, 1963-1969 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Fellowship Committee, 1967-1970 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Finance Committee, 1960-1969 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Finance Committee, 1974-1976 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Medicare Committee, 1961-1966 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Membership Committee, 1960-1965 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Membership Committee, 1965-1968 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Membership Committee, 1968-1970 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Membership Committee, 1968-1971 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Membership Committee, Billing Questionaire, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Memorial Committee, 1961-1970 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Nominating Committee, 1964-1966 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Nuclear Medicine Committee, 1972-1975 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Placement Committee, 1960-1967 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Professional Relationships Committee, 1957-1958 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Professional Relationships Committee, 1960-1970 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Program Committee, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Program Committee, 1965-1970 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Public Relations Committee, 1960-1970 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Publications Committee, 1964-1970 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Resident Award Committee, 1959-1963, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Standards and Protection Committee, 1964-1966 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Standards and Protection Committee, 1967-1970 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Technicians Committee, 1960-1969 (Box 4, Folder 18)
- Membership, 1916-1984; IV.
  Series IV contains membership records of the Society. There are 106 member files which contain photos, professional degrees, and publications. The member records are arranged alphabetically by last name. Additional records consist of annual member lists and membership forms.
  - Member Files, A-Z (Box 5, Folder 1-106)
  - List of Members, 1916-1955 (Box 5, Folder 107)
  - List of Members, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 108)
  - List of Officers, Directors, and Councilors, 1974-1984 (Box 5, Folder 109)
  - List of Female Members, 1955-1957 (Box 5, Folder 110)
  - Membership Certificate and Evaluation Forms, 1981-1983 (Box 5, Folder 111-113)
- Research and Publications, 1927-1975; V.
  Series V contains the Society's publications and medical research files. This series contains the Society's newletters.
  - American College of Radiology Quality Study, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Back Pain Research, 1937 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Blue Shield X-Ray Quality Review, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - The Bulletin of the Pennsylvania Radiological Society, 1974-1975 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Laryngography Research, 1927-1975 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - The PA Journal of Radiology, 1934-1944 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - The PA Journal of Radiology, 1945-1958 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Population Exposure to X-Rays, 1970 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Spalteholz Skull, 1973 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - X-Ray Desk Sign (Box 6, Folder 10)